<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cryptography on e3b0c442.io</title>
    <link>/tags/cryptography/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cryptography on e3b0c442.io</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/cryptography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The YubiKey; or, why are you still using a password in 2019?</title>
      <link>/post/yubikey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/yubikey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: I am not receiving any compensation either for what I&amp;rsquo;m saying here or
for the product links on this page. I think the YubiKey is a great product, and
I want to share why.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the upcoming release of macOS Catalina &amp;ndash; and with it, the end of the last
major browser holdout from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://fidoalliance.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;FIDO&lt;/a&gt; standards, I
wanted to take a moment to talk about the YubiKey and the promise of the
standards that it supports for secure internet authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we dive into the YubiKey itself, I&amp;rsquo;d like to explain why this is
important to me. The economic impact of compromised accounts is astronomical;
according to a 2018 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mcafee.com/us/resources/reports/restricted/economic-impact-cybercrime.pdf?utm_source=Press&amp;amp;utm_campaign=bb9303ae70-EMAIL_CAMPAIGN_2018_02_21&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_term=0_7623d157be-bb9303ae70-&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;
by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://csis.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Center for Strategic and International Studies&lt;/a&gt; in
collaboration with McAfee, the economic impact of cyber crime is nearly $600
billion per year, or 1% of total global GDP. At the same time, password security
is either misunderstood or ignored by both end users and system administrators
alike; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_the_most_common_passwords&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;according to multiple sources&lt;/a&gt;,
the most commonly-used password in recent years is &lt;code&gt;123456&lt;/code&gt;. In addition,
password requirements vary greatly amongst services, with many still enforcing
maximum length limits and the use of special characters (or limitation of
characters) &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/936/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;despite mathematical evidence&lt;/a&gt; that the use
of easy-to-remember long passphrases is far more secure than requiring multiple
special characters in a shorter password. Simply put - passwords need to be put
out to pasture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With what do we replace passwords? Public key cryptography has been widely-used
and battle-tested for decades &amp;ndash; every time you visit a site with the &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt;
URL scheme, you are using it! &amp;ndash; and while some implementations have been shown
to have weaknesses over time, the basic concepts are solid. As long as the
private key can be protected, public key cryptograhy is an effective method of
authenticating an end user and encrypting communications, which is where the
YubiKey comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not familiar with the YubiKey, it is a multi-protocol hardware
cryptographic token. The premise behind this kind of token is that the secret
key is stored on the token and the token itself performs cryptographic
operations using the key without making it accessible to the host system, thus
preventing the key from being siphoned off by an unscrupulous actor. The latest
generation YubiKey 5 family has support for the following protocols:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;USB HID&lt;/strong&gt;: these protocols take advantage of the capability of the YubiKey
to act as a keyboard and send data as keystrokes:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Static password: The YubiKey can generate a secure password that can be
combined with an easy-to-remember value to simulate a 2nd-factor auth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yubico OTP: A custom OTP implementation that relies on a shared key known
by the YubiKey and the server. Yubico provides this service for all
fresh-from-factory YubiKeys; if you don&amp;rsquo;t trust Yubico with your key, you can
run the service by yourself and reprogram your YubiKey with a new shared key.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OTP (One-time password)&lt;/strong&gt;: These protocols allow for time- or event-based
one-time passwords:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OATH-TOTP: This is the same protocol utilized by the nearly-ubiquitous
mobile authenticators out there. In the case of the YubiKey, the one-time
password values are read from the key with a special Yubico Authenticator
application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OATH-HOTP: This one-time password mechanism is not nearly as commonly used
due to its reliance on counters and susceptibility to synchronization
issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HMAC-SHA1 Challenge/Response: This protocol relies on a shared secret. The
remote party sends a challenge, and the YubiKey calculates the HMAC-SHA1 code
of the challenge using the shared secret, and returns it to the remote party.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CCID (Smart cards)&lt;/strong&gt;: These protocols allow the YubiKey to emulate smart
cards:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenPGP: The YubiKey acts as an OpenPGP smart card, with three key slots
available. The YubiKey then performs all sign/encrypt/decrypt operations using
the stored keys.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PIV: The YubiKey acts as a PIV card and can be accessed using the standard
PKCS#11 protocols. In addition to raw keys, the PIV applet can store
certificates and generate CSRs, allowing for the keys to be certified and have
enforced expiration and revocation capabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FIDO (web authentication)&lt;/strong&gt;: These protocols allow for the usage of public
key cryptography for authentication in the Web browser:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;U2F, aka CTAP1: This protocol allows for 2nd-factor authentication using the
private key stored on the YubiKey. It was never standardized beyond FIDO and
thus there are implementation and support issues across common browsers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FIDO2, aka CTAP2: This protocol is backwards-compatible with CTAP1, and
works in concert with the W3C WebAuthn standard to allow not only 2nd-factor
authentication, but completely passwordless authentication. This is the future
of web authentication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the fully-featured Yubikey 5 line, Yubico offers a &amp;ldquo;Security Key&amp;rdquo;
line which only support the FIDO protocols. For the majority of people out
there, this is sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.w3.org/TR/webauthn/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;WebAuthn&lt;/a&gt; is a recently ratified standard by
the W3C specifying a JavaScript API for facilitating authentication with public
key cryptography. This works together with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://fidoalliance.org/specs/fido-v2.0-rd-20170927/fido-client-to-authenticator-protocol-v2.0-rd-20170927.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CTAP device protocols&lt;/a&gt;
to enable the web browser to communicate with a CTAP-compatible USB device and
use it to securely authenticate a user to a service. Per the &lt;a href=&#34;https://fidoalliance.org/fido2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;FIDO2&lt;/a&gt;
website: &lt;code&gt;FIDO2 cryptographic login credentials are unique across every website, never leave the user’s device and are never stored on a server. This security model eliminates the risks of phishing, all forms of password theft and replay attacks.&lt;/code&gt; The FIDO2 protocol also supports requiring a local second
factor such as physical presence (push the button) or a PIN. In the case of a
PIN, this can be a simpler value as it is never transmitted over the Internet
nor stored outside of the device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I utilize my YubiKey 4 as much as possible. I use the PIV applet to log in
locally to my computers; the OpenPGP  applet to store my PGP auth, signing, and
encryption keys that I use for signing git commits or remotely logging into
servers. I utilize Yubico OTP as a second factor on my most sensitive servers as
well as the secnod factor on my password manager. I utilize FIDO U2F wherever
possible (Google, AWS, Facebook). I understand I am a power user, and that many
of these use cases are quite advanced, but I simply see too much value in
eschewing the world of the password and moving exclusively to public-key
cryptography, now that I have the tools to do it. I only wish more things
supported it, e.g. LUKS, which still requires a passphrase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of your level of expertise, I hope you are at least using a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.yubico.com/products/security-key-3/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Security Key&lt;/a&gt;. If not, get
one ASAP, and pressure every provider that does not yet support WebAuthn/FIDO2
to build that support as soon as possible. Hopefully we can start seeing that
$600 billion number trend downward as more people adopt YubiKeys or other
FIDO2-compliant devices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code 2015 Day 4: The Ideal Stocking Stuffer</title>
      <link>/post/advent-2015-c-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2019 03:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/advent-2015-c-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m back for a second time today since this puzzle is fairly straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santa needs help mining some AdventCoins (very similar to bitcoins) to use as gifts for all the economically forward-thinking little girls and boys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, he needs to find MD5 hashes which, in hexadecimal, start with at least &lt;strong&gt;five zeroes&lt;/strong&gt;. The input to the MD5 hash is some secret key (your puzzle input, given below) followed by a number in decimal. To mine AdventCoins, you must find Santa the lowest positive number (no leading zeroes: &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;, &amp;hellip;) that produces such a hash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your secret key is &lt;code&gt;abcdef&lt;/code&gt;, the answer is &lt;code&gt;609043&lt;/code&gt;, because the MD5 hash of &lt;code&gt;abcdef609043&lt;/code&gt; starts with five zeroes &lt;code&gt;(000001dbbfa...&lt;/code&gt;), and it is the lowest such number to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your secret key is &lt;code&gt;pqrstuv&lt;/code&gt;, the lowest number it combines with to make an MD5 hash starting with five zeroes is &lt;code&gt;1048970&lt;/code&gt;; that is, the MD5 hash of &lt;code&gt;pqrstuv1048970&lt;/code&gt; looks like &lt;code&gt;000006136ef...&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, we&amp;rsquo;ll start with breaking down the problem into discrete parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the input&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert a number to a string&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combine the input and the number string&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the MD5 digest of the combined string&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check that the first five digits of the digest are &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than write our own MD5 hashing implementation, we will use the well-known
and commonly-installed OpenSSL library&amp;rsquo;s implementation. You&amp;rsquo;ll need to make
sure that your linker pulls in the OpenSSL library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s write some code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;int main(int argc, char const *argv[])
{
    /* check that filename was provided */
    if (argc &amp;lt; 2)
    {
        fprintf(stderr, &amp;quot;Must provide filename of input file\n&amp;quot;);
        return -1;
    }

    /* read the file into memory */
    char *input;
    int filesize = read_file_to_buffer(&amp;amp;input, argv[1]);
    if (filesize &amp;lt; 0)
    {
        fprintf(stderr, &amp;quot;File read failed: %s\n&amp;quot;, strerror(errno));
        return -1;
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of completion, this is our standard prelude of verifying the
command-line argument and reading the input file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;    printf(&amp;quot;Day 4:\n&amp;quot;);

    /* initialize variables */
    int i = 1;
    char buf[strlen(input) + 11];
    memset(buf, 0, strlen(input) + 11);
    strcpy(buf, input);
    unsigned char digest[16];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We print our preamble, then initialize some variables. Note that I&amp;rsquo;m doing this
outside of a loop so that we do not incur this cost in the loop. Our code will
be written in such a way that the variables do not need to be reinitialized on
every pass. Step by step we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The declaration of the iteration index &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt;, which is the number that will be
added to the input string on each pass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The declaration of the buffer which stores the whole string to be hashed. We
size from the input and then add 11 &amp;ndash; 10 for the maximum number of digits in a
32-bit integer, and 1 for the null terminator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The initialization of the string buffer. Ensuring all bytes are set to &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; now
will help us not need to re-initialize the variable on every loop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copying the input into the buffer&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating a buffer for the MD5 digest. MD5 digests are 128 bits, so we need a
16-byte buffer. Note that we do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have a null terminator here because this
is not a string.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;while (1)
{
    sprintf(buf + strlen(input), &amp;quot;%d&amp;quot;, i);
    MD5((const unsigned char *)buf, strlen(buf), digest);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we begin the loop. W se formatted print to append the string representation
of &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; to the buffer. Notice that we are using pointer arithmetic to point to
the first index in the buffer after the original input string. Because the
numbers will only ever increase, we will overwrite this on each loop and not
need to reinitialize the variable. We then get the MD5 digest of the constructed
string.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, one might be tempted to use formatted print to output the
hexadecimal representation of the digest. &lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t!&lt;/em&gt; String formatting operations
are computationally expensive, and we have the information we need to solve
the problem without doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;        if (digest[0] == 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; digest[1] == 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; digest[2] &amp;lt; 16)
            break;
        i++;
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the ratio of bytes to hex characters is 1:2; that is, each byte of the
digest would translate to two hex characters. With this in mind, remember that
this digest is just one big number; so, rather than convert the number back to
a string, let&amp;rsquo;s just check the number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are searching for a digest where the first five digits of the hexadecimal
representation of the digest are &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;. For bytes 0 and 1, this is easy: the value
of the byte must be 0. For byte 2, it requires a little bit more thought, since
only the first digit must be zero. In this case, it&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of places
like in decimal math. There are 16 possible hexadecimal digits, so any value
of the byte that is less than 16 will have the first hex digit as 0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By checking this way and avoiding the string conversion, we cut our compute
usage down by 10-100x, which is important in this exercise as hashing is not a
fast operation, relatively speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;    printf(&amp;quot;\tSolution 1: %d\n&amp;quot;, i);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have our solution, which is the current value of &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt;. Once this is
validated, our second puzzle appears:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now find one that starts with six zeroes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that&amp;rsquo;s succinct, isn&amp;rsquo;t it? Literally all we need to do at this point is
resume the loop right where we left off, making one change: we can check that
byte 2 of the digest is equal to zero, rather than less than 16:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;    while (1)
    {
        sprintf(buf + strlen(input), &amp;quot;%d&amp;quot;, i);
        MD5((const unsigned char *)buf, strlen(buf), digest);

        if (digest[0] == 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; digest[1] == 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; digest[2] == 0)
            break;
        i++;
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t even need to reset &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; here, since by definition a digest can&amp;rsquo;t start
with six zeroes without starting with five. In the circumstance that the first
digest that begins with five zeroes also begins with six zeroes, the first
iteration of our loop will catch it because we broke out of the previous loop
before incrementing the index, and we don&amp;rsquo;t increment until the end of the loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have our solution, and can print it and clean up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;    printf(&amp;quot;\tSolution 2: %d\n&amp;quot;, i);

    free(input);
    return 0;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we put it all together, we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;rdquo;&amp;lsquo;c
#include &lt;errno.h&gt;
#include &lt;openssl/md5.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;
#include &lt;string.h&gt;
#include &amp;ldquo;common.h&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;int main(int argc, char const &lt;em&gt;argv[])
{
    /&lt;/em&gt; check that filename was provided */
    if (argc &amp;lt; 2)
    {
        fprintf(stderr, &amp;ldquo;Must provide filename of input file\n&amp;rdquo;);
        return -1;
    }&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/* read the file into memory */
char *input;
int filesize = read_file_to_buffer(&amp;amp;input, argv[1]);
if (filesize &amp;lt; 0)
{
    fprintf(stderr, &amp;quot;File read failed: %s\n&amp;quot;, strerror(errno));
    return -1;
}

printf(&amp;quot;Day 4:\n&amp;quot;);

/* initialize variables */
int i = 1;
char buf[strlen(input) + 11];
memset(buf, 0, strlen(input) + 11);
strcpy(buf, input);
unsigned char digest[16];

/* find the first matching digest */
while (1)
{
    sprintf(buf + strlen(input), &amp;quot;%d&amp;quot;, i);
    MD5((const unsigned char *)buf, strlen(buf), digest);

    if (digest[0] == 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; digest[1] == 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; digest[2] &amp;lt; 16)
        break;
    i++;
}

printf(&amp;quot;\tSolution 1: %d\n&amp;quot;, i);

/* find the first matching digest */
while (1)
{
    sprintf(buf + strlen(input), &amp;quot;%d&amp;quot;, i);
    MD5((const unsigned char *)buf, strlen(buf), digest);

    if (digest[0] == 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; digest[1] == 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; digest[2] == 0)
        break;
    i++;
}

printf(&amp;quot;\tSolution 2: %d\n&amp;quot;, i);

free(input);
return 0;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;}
```&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
